Rafael Lacerda

rafaelplmelo@gmail.com Toronto, ON, Canada (647) 878 9650

Career Objective

Adaptable professional with ~5 years of experience and proven knowledge in data science, natural language processing and machine learning engineering. I aim to leverage my skills and experience to fulfill your company's data science and machine learning needs.

Education

MSc. in Applied Computing, Sep 2016 — Dec 2017

University of Toronto, Department of Computer Science

- Courses: Natural Language Processing, Computational Neuroscience, Probabilistic Learning and Reasoning.
- Recipient of 30k Mitacs scholarship (2x terms).

BSc. in Economics, Aug 2011 — Jul 2014

Universidade Presbiteriana Mackenzie, Department of Applied Social Sciences

- Final thesis on a time series model to measure the effects of uncertainty brought upon by Federal intervention on oil policy.
- 6 month internship at a hedge fund (Kondor Invest, risk office).

Work Experience

Machine Learning Engineer, May 2017 — Feb 2019

Ross Intelligence, Toronto, ON

- Developed a state-of-the-art legal research system that surpassed IBM Watson's performance, leveraging deep learning, NLP and legal domain knowledge.
- Involved in all stages of Research, Development and Deployment in a distributed architecture.

Treasury Analytics, Aug 2014 — April 2016

OR Investimentos, São Paulo, Brazil

- Developed Business Intelligence systems to monitor aggregate treasury risk daily. Used Python, VBA, PL/SQL.
- Developed models to estimate bank risk when CDS spreads were unavailable.
- Created a system to manage 300+ regional branches' bank balances, saving over 3MM USD monthly by optimizing cash efficiency.

Head of Customer Service, Jan 2013 — Nov 2013

Zocprint, São Paulo, Brazil

- Developed and grew a new data-driven customer service department within the organization.
- Implemented data collection and processes to automatically close the feedback loop to the operations department. Used Python, MySQL, BPMN, VBA.
- Hired and managed up to 9 CS agents.

Frameworks

- Machine Learning: Python, R, Tensorflow, Pandas, Scikit-learn, Solr, Spacy.
- Software Engineering: SQL, NoSQL, Redis, Docker, Travis CI, REST APIs, AWS ecosystem.